<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>http://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/</id>
    <title>mojolicious.io</title>
    <updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent.atom" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/" rel="alternate" />
    <generator version="0.087">Statocles</generator>

    <entry>
        <id>http://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/11/30/mojolicious-advent-2017/</id>
        <title>Mojolicious Advent 2017</title>
        <link href="http://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/11/30/mojolicious-advent-2017/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>I&#39;m happy to announce that I&#39;ll be running a Mojolicious Advent Calendar this year!</p>

<p>For those of you who are unaware, an advent calendar is a way to count down to Christmas through December.
In many cases, the act of marking each day also provides a treat, usually chocolate.
All told, 24 days are marked, one for each day from Dec 1 to Dec 24, Christmas Eve.</p>

<p>I&#39;m not sure exactly how this moved into coding circles, but there is now a tradition of doing a similar countdown for programmers.
The treats are little bits of wisdom on some programming topic.</p>

<p>Perl has <a href="http://www.perladvent.org/">http://www.perladvent.org/</a> which has run for quite a long time.
Other calendars have popped up for other languages and I&#39;m told it is even migrating to non-coding maker-type spaces!</p>

<p>This year I&#39;ve decided that I&#39;d like there to be one for the <a href="http://mojolicious.org">Mojolicious Web Framework</a>.
My desire is partly to put out some common starting tips and tricks and partly due to some recent additions that could really do with some extra publicity (they&#39;re cool, just wait!).</p>

<p>At least at the moment it is just me so, in the hopes of actually completing it, some posts might be brief.
Some calendars try to use holiday themes in the posts, which I may do it the muse is upon me, but I make no promises.</p>

<p>I hope you&#39;ll enjoy no matter what religious or non-religious winter holidays you celebrate!</p>


                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="http://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
    </entry>
</feed>

