<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/full/</id>
    <title>mojolicious.io</title>
    <updated>2017-12-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/full.atom" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/full/" rel="alternate" />
    <generator version="0.087">Statocles</generator>

    <entry>
        <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/04/day-4-dont-fear-the-full-app/</id>
        <title>Day 4: Don&#39;t Fear the Full App</title>
        <author><name>Joel Berger</name></author>
        <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/04/day-4-dont-fear-the-full-app/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>One of the most common misconceptions about Mojolicious is that there is a large difference between the declarative &quot;Lite&quot; apps that we have seen so far and large-scale structured &quot;Full&quot; apps.
Nothing could be further from the truth.
<a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious/Lite">Mojolicious::Lite</a> is a very tiny wrapper around the so-called &quot;Full&quot; app architecture, giving it the approachable keyword syntax.</p>

<p>Because it is much nicer to have concise single-file examples for documentation most of Mojolicious&#39; documentation uses Lite syntax most of the time.
It is understandable that people worry about migrating (or as we call it &quot;growing&quot;) even once their apps would benefit from Object-Oriented structure; after all the docs seem geared towards Lite apps.
However, let those fears go, the transition is easy.
And once you understand it, the documentatation examples are trivial to translate.</p>

<p>Plus, Mojolicious comes with two forms of help when transitioning.
The first is the <a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious/Guides/Growing">Growing Guide</a> which covers everything this post will but from the perspective of porting an existing application (which I won&#39;t duplicate here).
The second is the <a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious/Command/inflate">inflate command</a> which can even start you on the process by moving your templates from the data section and into their own files.</p>

<p>That said, in order to futher demystify things, I&#39;m going to cover some of the differences and pull back the curtain on the Lite syntax itself.</p>

                <p><a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/04/day-4-dont-fear-the-full-app/#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>

                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/lite/">lite</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/full/">full</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/growing/">growing</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2017-12-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
        <category term="lite" />
        <category term="full" />
        <category term="growing" />
    </entry>
</feed>

