<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/html/</id>
    <title>mojolicious.io</title>
    <updated>2018-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/html.atom" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/html/" rel="alternate" />
    <generator version="0.093">Statocles</generator>

    <entry>
        <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/15/practical-web-content-munging/</id>
        <title>Day 15: Practical Web Content Munging</title>
        <author><name>Joe Cooper</name></author>
        <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/15/practical-web-content-munging/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>Following brian d foy&#39;s great <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/05/compound-selectors/">write-up of using Mojo::DOM selectors from Day 5</a>, I thought it&#39;d be fun to talk about some website migration scripts I recently built using <a href="https://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojo/UserAgent">Mojo::UserAgent</a> and <a href="https://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojo/DOM">Mojo::DOM</a>, in order to show some basic practical usage of these modules. I&#39;ve never really used Mojo before, but I recently needed to migrate a website that hasn&#39;t had a redesign in about 15 years, and it seemed like a great fit for my content mangling needs. In the past I would have used regexes, and probably would have spent at least as much time manually massaging the input or output into the right shape as I spent writing code. Mojo::DOM made it easy for me, a Mojolicious beginner, to get the results I wanted really quickly.</p>

<h2>From Static Site to Static Site Generator</h2>

<p>The problem I set out to solve was taking an old static website that was once hosted on SourceForge.net and migrating it to an exciting new...um...static website. But, this time, it&#39;ll be a modern take on a static website. Instead of editing HTML by hand and using home-built page munging scripts that would do things like insert news items or changelog entries at the top of the content div using regexes, I&#39;ll be using a modern static website generator. There are several to choose from, including the well-known Jekyll, which is written in Ruby, Hugo, built with Go, and Statocles, which is in Perl and runs this site. For my project, I chose <a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</a>, for its speed and maturity.</p>

                <p><a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/15/practical-web-content-munging/#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>

                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/css/">css</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/html/">html</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2018-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
        <category term="css" />
        <category term="html" />
    </entry>
</feed>

