<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/session/</id>
    <title>mojolicious.io</title>
    <updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/session.atom" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/session/" rel="alternate" />
    <generator version="0.088">Statocles</generator>

    <entry>
        <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/16/day-16-the-secret-life-of-sessions/</id>
        <title>Day 16: The Secret Life of Sessions</title>
        <author><name>Joel Berger</name></author>
        <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/16/day-16-the-secret-life-of-sessions/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>As you all know, HTTP is a stateless protocol.
In Mojolicious applications the session is used to maintain state between requests.
These sessions are managed by the application&#39;s <a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious/#sessions">session manager</a>.</p>

<p>During each request, the <a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious/Controller#session">session</a> is just another hash reference attached to the controller, in some ways like the <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/02/day-2-the-stash">stash</a>, except this one persists between requests.
Mojolicious does this by encoding the structure, first as JSON then Base64.
It then signs the resulting string using HMAC-SHA1 and the application&#39;s <a href="http://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojolicious#secrets">secret</a> to prevent tampering and stores it as a cookie on the response to the client.</p>

<p>On subsequent requests, the client sends the cookie along with the request (as cookies do).
Mojolicious then checks if the document and signature validate against the secret, if so the cookie is decoded and made available again via the session method.</p>

<p>Two important things to note.
First, though the data is safe from tampering, it isn&#39;t encrypted; a savvy user can decode the cookie and see the stored data, so don&#39;t put anything in it that shouldn&#39;t be seen.
Second, this is only useful if the secret is strong and safe.
If not, the client could forge a cookie that appeared to come from your application, possibly with catastrophic results!
So while Mojolicious makes it easy, a little care can go a long way toward keeping your session data safe and trusted.</p>

                <p><a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/16/day-16-the-secret-life-of-sessions/#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>

                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/session/">session</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2017-12-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
        <category term="session" />
    </entry>
</feed>

