<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/non-web/</id>
    <title>mojolicious.io</title>
    <updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/non-web.atom" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/non-web/" rel="alternate" />
    <generator version="0.097">Statocles</generator>

    <entry>
        <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/14/a-practical-example-of-mojo-dom/</id>
        <title>Day 14: A Practical Example of Mojo::DOM</title>
        <author><name>Chris Seigman</name></author>
        <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/14/a-practical-example-of-mojo-dom/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>With recent versions of Mojolicious, <a href="https://mojolicious.org/perldoc/Mojo/DOM">Mojo::DOM</a> gained a lot of power that I have been excited to try, but haven&#39;t had the time for.  Recently, I had a problem at my real job (in Engineering, Procurement, and Construction, or EPC for short) that I solved with Mojo::DOM (and other parts of Mojolicious) in a very short time – including learning how to use Mojo::DOM, which I had never done before.</p>

                <p><a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2018/12/14/a-practical-example-of-mojo-dom/#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>

                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/xml/">xml</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/non-web/">non-web</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
        <category term="xml" />
        <category term="non-web" />
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/21/day-21-virtually-a-lumberjack/</id>
        <title>Day 21: Virtual(ly a) Lumberjack</title>
        <author><name>CandyAngel</name></author>
        <link href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/21/day-21-virtually-a-lumberjack/" rel="alternate" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>What do you do when you want to split up a stream of data in real-time while
giving the user instructions?</p>

<p>This is just what I wanted to do to aid in reverse-engineering the USB
protocol of Virtual Reality devices known as Head Mounted Displays (HMD), for
the <a href="http://www.openhmd.net/">OpenHMD</a> project.</p>

<p>HMDs are used to create virtual reality environments. When worn, two slightly
different images are drawn to each side of the screen, with each side visible
to only one eye. This imitates binocular vision and creates an image with a
feeling of depth. By tracking the rotation of the unit, the user can then look
around this environment.</p>

<p>The recent resurgence of Virtual Reality devices can be attributed to the Rift
DK1, released by Oculus in March 2013.</p>

<p>By logging the packets generated during each movement, we can compare the
content of each log to identify which bytes are related to which action. Such
movements include roll (tilting head side-to-side), pitch (looking up and
down) and yaw (turning left/right). Though position isn&#39;t tracked, we also
look for sway (left-right translation), surge (back and forth) and heave (up
and down) information as this is used in combination with the other values for
accurate tracking of rotation.</p>

<p>Mojo is an amazing toolkit for web development, as shown in previous
calendar entries, but using components of it can also solve problems in other
non-web spaces like these. Why use Mojo for this? Because it makes it <em>easy</em>.</p>

                <p><a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/2017/12/21/day-21-virtually-a-lumberjack/#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>

                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/advent/">advent</a>
                    <a href="https://mojolicious.io/blog/tag/non-web/">non-web</a>
                </p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2017-12-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="advent" />
        <category term="non-web" />
    </entry>
</feed>

